Abandoned artificial satellites.
Tanks jettisoned from shuttles.
（ナレーション）
使い捨てられた人工衛星
シャトルが切り離したタンク
ステーション建造時に出た廃棄物
Debris generated during
space station construction.
This trash, space debris, circles the Earth
at speeds approaching 8 kilometers per second.
これら 宇宙のゴミ
スペースデブリは―
秒速８キロメートル近い速度で
地球の周りを回っています
そんなデブリが
宇宙船とぶつかれば―
Should this debris collide with a spacecraft,
it could result in a terrible accident.
大きな事故に つながりかねません
そこで 人々は デブリを
回収する必要に迫られました
For this reason, mankind has been confronted
by the necessity of collecting this debris.
2075年―
This is a story of 2075, a time in which
this space garbage has become a problem.
これは 宇宙のゴミが
問題になった時代の物語
♪～
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
♪光が向かう場所へ
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
♪フロンティアへ
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
Phase 7
Extraterrestrial Girl
（ハチマキ）
俺たち人間は―
We humans aren't designed to spend
our entire lives in space.
宇宙空間で
一生を過ごすようには―
できていない
If you don't watch your diet and exercise,
you'll be sidelined before you know it,
筋トレや食事に
気をつけていないと―
あっという間に
ダウンしちまうし―
...and some people go crazy from staying
in a closed environment.
閉鎖環境で
精神のバランスを失う者もいる
Cosmic radiation
is unforgiving, too.
宇宙放射線も容赦がない
Folks who can't handle it all
turn right around and go home.
ついてこられないやつは
あっという間にゴーホームだ
ただ 病気やケガで すぐには
地球に帰れない場合がある
But there are times when sickness or injuries
keep you from going back to Earth right away.
だから月は―
That's why the moon is like a convalescent
home to folks like us who work in space.
俺たち宇宙で働く人間にとって
保養所みたいなもんだ
あ～ 結局のところ 俺たちは
地球から離れては生きていけない
So what it boils down to is that
we can't live away from the Earth.
That's just the way it is
right now.
それが 今の現実だ
（シャッター音）
（ハチマキ）ん？
Ramon-sama, your prescription is ready to
be picked up at the pharmacy window.
（ノノ）ハァ…
Senpai!
（タナベ）先輩
（ハチマキ）あっ
何だよ みんなそろって
How come you're all ganging up
on me like this?
What do you mean?
（タナベ）“何だ”って…
Aren't we allowed
to come visit you?
（フィー）
見舞いに来ちゃ いけないのか？
Oh, uh, I appreciate it.
なっ そ… そりゃ どうも
I guess this isn't
gonna work...
（ノノ）さすがに無理か
ハァ…
It'll take you a
week to recover?
（リュシー）全治１週間？
So you're going to spend all your time off
cooped up in the hospital?
（チェンシン）じゃあ 休暇中は
ずっと入院してるってことか
Geez, if I'd known this was gonna happen,
I would've stayed on Seven.
っとに… こんなことなら
セブンにいたほうがマシだった
They've been bouncing me
from room to room, too.
病室まで 転々と替えさせられてよ
But the ninjas have already
been discharged...
忍者さんは
もう みんな退院したのに
With all that stuff they do,
they're used to this 1/6 G.
やつらは 何だかんだ言って
６分の１Ｇに慣れてんだよ
Hachi, I took care of all the
paperwork from the hospital.
（フィー）ハチ
病院の手続き やっといたから
それと 「コスモノーツ」今週号
Also, here's this week's issue
of Cosmonauts.
Oh, and worker's compensation
isn't going to cover this.
あと 労災は下りないからね
Why not?!
I saved somebody...
（ハチマキ）
なんでだよ 俺は人助けを…
忍者ごっこで ケガしたんだろ？
You got hurt while
playing ninja, right?
ぐっ くっ… 黙ってろって
You should've kept
your mouth shut!
うそは いけませんよ
It's not good
to lie.
お前のお隣さんのせいで
こうなってるんだろ？
This happened to me because
of those neighbors of yours!
That's why I've been trying to
make you more comfortable.
だから いろいろ身の回りの世話を
してるんじゃないですか
（チェンシン）
ハチ いい機会だから―
Hachi, why don't you take advantage of this
opportunity and go back to Earth to recuperate?
地球ヘ帰って静養したらどうだ？
Hey, that's right!
そうですよ
You haven't been back for over a year, right?
You can patch things up with your father...
１年以上 帰ってないんでしょう？
お父さんとも仲直りして…
Give it a rest! Astronauts heal faster
when they're in space!
うるせえな！
宇宙飛行士は 宇宙にいるのが
いちばん治りが早いんだよ
That's a fine attitude
to have.
（ローランド）いい心掛けだ
（ハチマキ）あっ？
But you must not be getting enough physical
training if you hurt your leg that way.
（ローランド）
だが トレーニング不足だな
簡単に足を痛めるようでは
Who are you,
old man?
誰だ？ おっさん
I swear, kids nowadays
aren't worth their salt.
全く 最近の若いのは
だらしないな
You have it too easy. You're used to your
full pressure suits and Navstars.
１気圧服や ナブスターに慣れて
楽 しすぎるからだ
Like I said, who the
hell are you?
だから 誰なんだよ あんた
（アナウンス）
３０３号室の―
Harry Roland-sama of room 303, please come
to consultation room number one at once.
（アナウンス）
３０３号室の―
ハリー･ローランド様
あっ？
（ローランド）おっと 俺か
Oops, that's me.
（アナウンス）
至急 第１診察室まで―
お越しください
ハリー･ローランド
あの人がねえ
Harry Roland? That's him?
ハリー･ローランド
あの人がねえ
Repeating...
Do you know him?
Harry Roland-sama of room 303, please come
to consultation room number one at once.
知ってるんですか？
He's an astronaut first-grade with a
career spanning more than 20 years.
キャリア20数年の一等航宙士よ
He's one of the heroes on the first manned
exploration of the asteroid belt.
小惑星帯を
初めて有人探索したヒーローの１人
あんたたちが子供んときね
That was back when
you were kids.
Seems pretty spry for an old-timer.
What's he doing in the hospital?
えらく元気そうなおやじだけど
なんで入院してんだ？
It's pretty obvious that he didn't
hurt himself playing ninja.
忍者ごっこでケガしたんじゃ
ないのは 確かですね
Don't bring that
up again, damn it!
てめえ 蒸し返すんじゃねえよ
（タナベ）エヘヘヘヘ
（機械音声）いらっしゃいませ
Welcome.
Please click on the magazine you wish
to read, and overwrite the old file.
ご希望の雑誌を
クリックして書き換えてください
（シャッター音）
（ハチマキ）あっ
ご希望の雑誌を
クリックして書き換えてください
あっ… ああ
（シャッター音）
（ハチマキ）読む？
（ノノ）えっ？
Wanna read this?
「コスモノーツ」の今週号
地球環境特集やってるよ
It's this week's issue of Cosmonauts.
They're doing a special on Earth's environment.
I've already read it.
俺 もう読んじゃったから
Oh, thanks.
ありがとう
Well, see ya.
そんじゃ
あっ あ…
（ハチマキ）ん？
Um...
あの…
（ハチマキ）海って地球のだよね？
Oceans? You mean the ones
on Earth?
（ノノ）うん
Yeah.
（ハチマキ）教えろったって
俺も１年以上 帰ってないからな
I don't know what I can tell you about 'em.
I haven't been back there for a year.
Oh, you haven't?
（ノノ）そうなんだ
How long has it been since you came up here?
You look about the same age as...
君はここに来て どれくらいなの？
俺とそんなに変わりない…
（ノノ）12年
Twelve years.
Twelve...
じゅうに… 12年！？
Twelve years?!
うん
えーっと…
What disease could she have that would keep
her from going back to Earth for so long?
（ハチマキ）そんな長いこと
地球に帰れない病気って何だ？
12年ってことは
こう見えて 結構いい年なのか？
If she's been here twelve years, I guess
that means she's older than she looks.
No, don't think
about that.
いや そんなことは どうでもいい
うかつに病名とか聞いたりしちゃ
マズいよな やっぱ
I guess it'd be a bad idea to just come out
and ask her what disease she's got...
（ノノ）ん？
（ハチマキ）えーっと 海か
Well, let's see...
The ocean, huh?
Okay, the ocean. Well, the sea level's
risen in the past twelve years.
海だよな
12年前より
水位は上がってるけど…
俺の家(うち) 九十九里(くじゅうくり)のそばでさ
My family lives near Kujukuri.
Kuju?
くじゅう？
It's on the coast
of Japan.
日本の海岸
I always saw the ocean, so I never
gave it much thought.
いつも見てたから
気にしなかったけど―
I guess it's because I've been
living in space for nearly a year.
やっぱさ １年のほとんどを
宇宙で暮らしてるせいかな
こっちから見てると
なんだか やけにきれいに思えてさ
When you see it from out here, there's
something incredibly beautiful about it.
あっ いや…
Um. But there aren't many spots that are
clean enough to swim in, though.
実際 泳げるほど きれいな海なんて
ほとんどないよ
遠巻きに見てるほうが
よっぽどマシさ
I think it's a lot better to
look at it from a distance.
多分…
I guess.
ふーん
Nono-chan?
Time for your exam.
（看護師）ノノちゃーん 診察
Coming!
（ノノ）はーい
That reminds me, I need to
pick up my medication and...
そういや
俺も薬を取りに うっ あ…
Can I borrow this
until tomorrow?
あしたまで借りてていい？ これ
あっ いいよ あげる
That's okay.
You can keep it.
Really? Thanks!
ほんと？ ありがとう
（看護師）ノノちゃん
Nono-chan.
はーい
I'm coming!
Thanks a lot!
ほんとに ありがとう
（ハチマキ）あっ…
See ya!
（ノノ）それじゃあ
Twelve years, huh?
12年… か
Usually, extreme cases go back
to Earth for treatment.
（ハチマキ）普通 本格的な治療は
地球でやるもんだろうに
Twelve years...
12年…
俺には耐えられないな
I probably couldn't
handle that...
いや 耐えられる人間なんて
いるのか？
No, could any human
handle something like that?
♪～
That's too bad. We're on different
flights back, Cheng-Shin-san.
（リュシー）残念です
チェンシンさんと
別便になっちゃうなんて
If you see Hachi, could you tell him
that I'll be waiting for him on Seven?
ハチに会ったら伝えてくれる？
先に セブンで待ってるって
（リュシー）
タナベに言っておきます
I'll pass it along
to Tanabe.
She always coming by to bring him
changes of clothes and stuff.
ちょくちょく着替えとか
持っていってるみたいだから
責任 感じてるのかな
I wonder if she feels responsible
for what happened?
タナベさん 真面目だから
Tanabe sure is
thoughtful.
女の子が
男の見舞いに行く理由なんて―
Actually, there's only one reason that I can
think of for a girl to visit a boy in the hospital.
１つしかないと思いますけど？
（あくび）
（ドアの開く音）
あっ 何だよ？
毎日 来んなって言ってんだろ
Now what? Didn't I tell you
not to come here every day?
毎日なんて来てませんよ
おとといは部屋にいました
I don't come here every day.
I stayed home the day before yesterday.
（ハチマキ）何だ？ これ
What's that?
A get-well gift. It's an apple.
（タナベ）お見舞い リンゴです
You're kidding!
これが！？
They said it was grown
in lunar soil.
月の大地で育てたんですって
おいおい 大丈夫か？
Hey, are you sure
this is safe? I think it might have evolved into
something that isn't a fruit.
既に果物じゃないものに
進化してねえか？
You sure are lily-livered,
youngster.
（ローランド）
肝が小さいぞ 若いの
Space is full
of radiation.
宇宙ってのは
放射線でいっぱいなんだ
大気に守られていない
月の被ばく量は―
With no atmosphere to protect it, the moon gets
over 100 times the radiation the Earth does.
地球の100倍以上
（ハチマキ）
まっ 地球と同じように
育つわきゃねえよな
Well, I guess you can't expect 'em to
grow the same as they do on Earth...
It looks delicious,
doesn't it?
（タナベ）
おいしそうじゃないですか
Have you ever eaten
one of these?
お前 食べたことあんのか？ これ
Of course not.
まさか
You're trying to use me as your
poison tester, aren't you?!
（ハチマキ）てめえ
俺に毒味させるつもりだな？
Listen up, youngster.
いいか 若いの よく聞け
Pay close attention.
（ハチマキ）あ？
（ローランド）
スプートニクから100余年
It's been over a hundred years since Sputnik.
We astronauts made space the world it is today.
宇宙は 俺たち宇宙飛行士が
育ててきた世界だ
And there's no better place
for an astronaut to die.
死に場所も ここ以外にないぞ
I don't need you to tell me that.
That's how I plan to go.
あんたに言われなくたって
そのつもりだ
Gross.
まずっ…
（ハチマキ）あれ？
（ノノ）あっ…
Huh?
Thanks for the magazine
earlier, um...
こないだは ありがとう
えっと…
Hoshino Hachirota.
（ハチマキ）星野(ほしの)八郎太(はちろうた)
“ハチマキ”でいいよ
みんな そう呼んでる
Just call me Hachimaki.
Everybody else does.
Hachimaki?
（ノノ）ハチマキ？
ウフフッ 変な名前
That's a funny name. I'm...
私は…
（ハチマキ）ノノ
Nono. I heard that nurse
call you over earlier.
この間 看護師さんが呼んでた
“ノノちゃん”って
She called you Nono-chan.
アハッ フフッ
（ハチマキ）何か飲む？ おごるよ
Want something to drink? It's my treat.
（ノノ）あっ 私はいい
No thanks, I'm okay.
You could've let me treat you
to a juice, you know.
（ハチマキ）ジュースぐらい
遠慮しなくていいのに
They put me under this afternoon,
and now I can't get to sleep.
昼間 麻酔を使っちゃったから
眠れなくって 時間つぶしてた
I've been passing
the time here.
Oh, that's why.
なるほどね
You don't have your camera
with you today?
ああ 今日はカメラないの？
ん？ ああ
Nah.
I got it as a present
for my birthday.
お誕生日のお祝いに
もらったんだけどね
なんだか
撮ってみても実感が湧かなくって
But it didn't seem real, not even
when I took pictures of it.
ねえ ハチマキ
クジュのこと聞かせて
Say, Hachimaki, tell me about
that Kuju place.
ああ 九十九里浜？
Oh, you mean Kujukuri Beach?
Yeah.
うん
When I was in high school,
I was really into motorcycles.
俺 高校のとき
バイクにハマっててさ
潮風って
やっぱ機械には最悪なんだけど―
The salty wind off the sea is really bad for machines, but I rode my bike along the seaside roads all the time anyway.
でも 海沿いの道ばかり走ってた
I never thought about it much,
but I guess I really loved it. Being able to see the ocean, I mean.
あんまり
考えたことなかったけど―
きっと好きだったんだろうな
海が見えるの
（ノノ）ここから見える？
Can you see it
from here?
（ハチマキ）あ？
いや 反対側になっちまってるかな
No, it's on the Earth's
far side right now.
I sure would like to see
your ocean, Hachimaki!
見てみたいな ハチマキの海
（ハチマキ）う… えっ？
ああ そのうちな…
じゃあ 俺 部屋に戻るね
Um, I'm sure you
will someday.
Well, I should get back
to my room.
Me, too. I get in trouble
if I stay up too late.
（ノノ）私も
あんまり夜更かしすると
怒られちゃう
All pharmacists participating in the third set of clinical trials, please meet at the Central Pharmaceutical Affairs office.
（アナウンス）３番
臨床参加する薬剤師は―
中央薬事課に集合してください
Three!
（ハチマキ）３
（ノノ）４
Four.
Five!
ダウト
I doubt it!
（ハチマキ）
たあっ 終わんねえよ これ
Geez, this game is never
gonna end!
（ノノ）フフッ
はい ハチマキにあげる
Here you go, Hachimaki. They're all yours.
（ハチマキ）おう タナベ
Hey, Tanabe!
Sorry about that. They said they have to have
my company I.D. For their release forms.
悪(わり)いな 退院の手続きに
どうしても社員証が要るって
That's okay.
（タナベ）いえ
はい
（ハチマキ）おう サンキュー
Here.
Oh, thank you.
ねえ 一緒にやらない？
Hey, wanna join in?
It's more fun with three people.
３人のほうが面白いんだ これ
With just two people, it takes
forever to finish a game.
２人だと なかなか終わんないの
Know how to play I Doubt lt?
ダウトって知ってる？
Um, I have plans
after this, so...
あの… このあと 約束があるから
Oh, you do? That's too bad.
そっか 残念
（ノノ）私 残り３枚だよ はい ６
I have three cards left. Okay, six!
（ハチマキ）じゃ ダウト
I doubt it.
Wrong! It was a six!
（ノノ）はずれ ６でした
You're kidding me!
（ハチマキ）うそだろ？
（ハチマキとノノの笑い声）
♪～
I'm only on the moon through
tomorrow, you know?
（タナベ）ほら
私が月にいられるのって―
あしたまででしょう？
That's why you called me up
all of a sudden?
I wanted to come
to Apollo Park.
（タナベ）アポロ公園って
来てみたかったんだ
リュシーと違って―
Unlike you guys. I won't be able to come
back here for a long time, Lucie.
今度 月に来られるのは
だいぶ先のことだから
あっ…
うわあ “ムーン煎餅”だって
This says "Moon Sembei"!
Look, look, I knew
they'd have them!
That's so cool!
ほらほら
やっぱりあるんだ すご～い
日本のお菓子？
Is it a Japanese
snack food?
I wonder how these are different
from regular rice crackers.
これ 普通のお煎餅と
何が違うのかな
Excuse me.
（男性）すいません
（タナベ）はい
Yes?
（女性）
写真 撮ってもらえませんか？
Would you mind taking
our picture?
あっ…
We were hoping to get a picture of us
with Apollo 11 in the background.
（女性）あの… バックに
アポロ11号が入るように―
撮ってほしいんだけど
（タナベ）ん…
ここからだと
アポロ11号は全部 入りませんよ
You won't be able to get all of
Apollo 11
in the picture from here.
ああ ほら
イーグルだったら大丈夫ですよ
Oh, hey! You get get all of the
Eagle module to fit, though!
あっ あっちで撮りましょう
Let's take it over there.
This is your camera, right?
カメラ これですよね
I'm not very good with electronics,
but this one's easy to operate, right?
私 メカ苦手なんですけど
簡単ですよね？ これ
（男性１）どうです？
退院したら行ってみませんか？
What do you think? Want to go there
after we get out of here?
（男性２）いいですね
That's a good idea. But my muscles have been
shot ever since I was admitted here.
あっ でも入院して
体が なまってますからな
だからですよ
That's why you should go.
You've got to get up and moving.
体 動かさないと
気持ちいいもんですよ
It feels great. The ball flies
six times farther than on Earth.
地球の６倍 飛びますからね
You feel like you've turned into the
main character of a golf comic!
自分がゴルフ漫画の
主人公になった気分ですよ
I guess I'll try to make
a black hole in one, then!
（男性２）
じゃあ ギャラクシーショット
打てますかね？
（男性１）ハハッ…
（医師１）いたか？
（医師２）いえ Ｂ棟にも
Did you find him?
No. He's not in Ward B, either.
（ローランド）
ハァー フゥー ハァー フゥー
ハァー
（医師１）そっちはどうだ？
How about you?
I've double-checked the monitors,
but there's no sign of him.
（医師２）モニターを
再チェックしたが見当たらない
Maybe we should work on the assumption
that he isn't inside the hospital anymore.
（医師３）院内には
もういないと考えたほうがいいか
Maybe we shouldn't
have told him.
（医師１）
やはり 告知がマズかったかも
（医師２）レスキューを呼ぶか？
Should I call
search and rescue?
That'd cause trouble. Let's look for him
by ourselves for a while longer.
（医師１）それはマズい
もう少し 我々で捜そう
（フィー）忘れ物はないか？
Are you sure you
have everything?
Yeah. I guess it's time to go.
（ハチマキ）ああ さてと
Where's Roland-san?
（フィー）ローランドさんは？
I don't know, I haven't seen him
since last night.
いや ゆうべから
ずっと見かけないけど
Oh, really? I wanted to introduce myself
while I had the chance.
（フィー）そうか せっかくだから
挨拶したかったな
ただの口うるさいおやじだって
Aw, he's just a foul-mouthed
old geezer.
あっ… んぐぐぐ
（ノノ）ハチマキ？
（ハチマキ）あっ
Hachimaki!
今日 退院なんだっけ？
They say you're being
released today?
I was gonna stop by
and say hi on my way out.
あとで挨拶に行こうと
思ってたんだけど
（ノノ）地球に帰るの？
Are you going
back to Earth?
I have a job to do, so it'll be a long, long
time before I can get back to Earth.
仕事があるからな
地球に帰れるのは ずっと先
Bye.
（ハチマキ）んじゃ
If you ever get hurt, feel free
to come back here.
ケガしたら またおいで 遠慮なく
ハハッ そうする
Sure, I'll do that.
Say, Nono.
About your...
なあ ノノ 君の…
（ノノ）ん？
あっ いや 元気で
Forget it.
Take care of yourself.
フフッ
あっ…
（ハチマキ）“元気で”？
"Take care of yourself"?
AM I SOME KIND
OF MORON?!
（ハチマキ）バッカか！ 俺はー！
（クラクション）
（フィー）ふーん 12年もね
Twelve years, huh?
You'd think that would make things worse.
なんか
かえって悪くなりそうだけど
I never even asked her
what disease she had...
（ハチマキ）
結局 病名は聞かずじまいだったな
ハァ…
（フィー）フッ
The Sea of Tranquility, huh?
（ハチマキ）静かの海… か
It would've been great
if this was a real sea...
ここが本物の海なら
よかったのにな
（フィー）はっ！
いたあっ
Hachi! Over there!
What the hell did you
slam on the brakes for?!
何だよ いきなり
ああ？ 人か？ おい
Hey, is that a person?
（アナウンス）静(しず)かの海(うみ)
月面宇宙港をご利用いただき―
Thank you for using the Sea of Tranquility
lunar surface spaceport.
誠に ありがとうございます
How's he look, Fee?
Is he in trouble?
（ハチマキ）どうだ？ フィー
ヤバいのか？ その人
（フィー）
スーツ内の窒素濃度が異常に高い
The nitrogen levels in his suit
are abnormally high.
Guess he didn't do enough
pre-breathing, either.
ろくな
プリブリージングもしなかったな
（ハチマキ）
１気圧服じゃないのか？
That isn't a
full pressure suit?
（フィー）血中窒素が気化して
体中で空気塞栓を起こしてる
The nitrogen that was in his blood is vaporizing.
It's causing air embolisms all over his body.
重度の減圧症だ
He's got severe
decompression sickness.
He's still breathing, right?
If we get him back to the hospital...
息はあるんだろ？ 病院に運べよ…
あっ ローランドさん？
Roland-sama?
ベテランなんだろ？
Isn't he supposed to be a veteran?!
How could he make such a rookie mistake?!
なんで
こんな初歩的なミスすんだよ？
（フィー）
私に聞いたって知るもんか！
Don't ask me!
How should I know?!
You don't think... Suicide?
（ハチマキ）まさか 自殺？
（フィー）
バカ言ってんじゃないの！
Don't be stupid! I'll carry him,
so you get the airlock and...
私が担ぐから
車に戻ってエアーロッ…
（ローランド）
そっとしといてくれんか
Could you just
leave me here...?
（フィー）あっ
（ハチマキ）えっ
It's time for me
to go...
もう潮時なんだよ
ローランドさん
Roland-sama?
I have leukemia.
（ローランド）白血病なんだ
'Cause I was out in space
for 20 years.
20年も宇宙にいたからな
俺ほど宇宙を愛している者は
いないというのに―
Nobody loves space more than me...
How could she do this to me?
随分な仕打ちじゃないか
I...
俺は…
俺を勝手に引退させるな
Don't you dare
force me to retire!
I still have plenty of good...
まだまだ俺は…
（ハチマキ）フィー
（フィー）やってる！
- Fee.
I'm trying, but judging from his air tank,
he's been out here for over ten hours.
（ハチマキ）フィー
（フィー）やってる！
だが 酸素ボンベの減りからして
もう10時間以上…
Hey, old man! Hang in there!
You've had a 20 year career, right?
（ハチマキ）
おい じいさん しっかりしろよ！
20年のキャリアがあるんだろ
But you can't... get rid
of me that easily.
（ローランド）だが ハハッ
そう簡単に フラれはせんぞ
これで俺は… 俺も お前の―
This way, I'll... I'll be part...
一部… に…
I'll be part of you...
はっ
I guess they're putting us
on another flight...
（フィー）定期便は振り替えか
Tanabe says she'll wait
for us at the spaceport.
タナベ 宇宙港で待ってるって
なあ フィー
Say, Fee...
何？
What?
Let's say that there really is
something like God out there...
神様… みたいなものが
いるとしてさ
（ノノ）ん？ ハチマキ？
Hachimaki?
I guess he must really
hate us humans.
多分 そいつ
俺たち人間が嫌いなんだろうな
（フィー）ん…
（ハチマキ）地球も汚して
月も汚して おまけにデブリ
We pollute the Earth, we pollute the moon,
and we produce all that debris, too.
露骨に帰れって言われてるのに
気がつかない―
Maybe we're like annoying guests
who don't take the hint when he's telling us
point-blank to go home.
迷惑な客なんじゃないかな 俺たち
（フィー）ハチマキ
Hachimaki!
あ ぐっ
あっ…
（ハチマキ）な… くっ この…
What the...
You bi...
（フィー）
シャキッとしろ！ デブリ屋だろ
Shape up, damn it!
You're a debris hauler, aren't you?
You're a grown man,
so quit your moping!
何さ 大の男がウジウジと
神様が何だって？
What's this about God? Are we supposed
to pack up and go back down to Earth?
だったら地球(オカ)に降りるっての？
もう ここは人間の世界だ
This is humanity's
world now!
ああ…
そうとも
That's right. Curling up and hiding in a
warm, safe place won't solve anything.
温かい所に引きこもっていても
何の解決にも なりゃしないんだ
The world can't get by without space
resources anymore, and you know it!
今更 宇宙資源なしで
世の中が回るわけないでしょ！
若いのが そんな ふ抜けじゃ―
Roland-san's gonna roll over in his grave if he
finds out what cowards you young people are!
ローランドさんだって
安眠できないぞ
とにかく 今は
足を治すことだけ考えなさい
Anyway, just focus on
your foot getting better!
Stupid Hachi!
バカハチ！
（ハチマキ）ああ…
（ドアの閉まる音）
（フィー）いってえ あの石頭
He really does have
a head like a rock...
はあ… あっ
あいたたた ハァ…
Ow...
（ドアの開く音）
Hachimaki?
You came back?
（ノノ）
ハチマキ 戻ってきたの？
（ハチマキ）まあ いろいろあって
Well, something
came up...
You heard that?
Scary lady, isn't she?
聞いてた？
おっかないやつだろ？
グーで殴りやがんの
She whacks people
upside the head.
ハチマキ もう１個
酸素ボンベ 取ってこられる？
Hachimaki, do you think you
can find another oxygen tank?
I'm on my way to...
これから…
（ハチマキ）え？
There's an airlock up ahead that has
full pressure suits stored in it.
（ノノ）この先に １気圧服の
置いてあるエアロックがあって―
They won't find out if we go out
onto the surface from there.
そこから月面に出ても
なぜか バレないんだ
ないしょだよ
Don't tell anybody.
The surface?
月面？
あっ…
The city just entered
the nightside.
（ノノ）
この町 さっき夜に入ったんだ
It's prettier outside at night.
It's full of stars.
夜のほうがきれいなんだよ
星だらけでね
でも 大人の人が
外に出させてくれないのよね
But the adults never let me go outside.
That's why I'm sneaking out.
だから こっそり
"The adults"? You're an
adult, too, aren't you?
大人の人って
君だって大人じゃないか
Oh, you don't know?
I'm 12 years old.
あっ そうか 12歳だよ 私
Oh, you are?
ああ そうなんだ
12歳！？
YOU'RE ONLY TWELVE?!
シーッ！
（ハチマキ）んぐんぐ…
プハッ ハァ ハァ…
I'm a Lunarian.
私ね ルナリアンなの
（ハチマキ）えっ
（ノノ）月生まれの月育ち
世界に４人しかいないんだって
I was born and raised
on the moon.
They say there are only
four of us in the whole world.
言わなかったっけ？
Didn't I tell you?
ああ…
（ノノ）父さんも母さんも
月で働いているんだ
My mom and dad
both work on the moon.
ここで
イルメナイト採掘プラントの―
They work here as engineers
in an ilmenite mining plant.
技師をしているの
By the time they found out
Mom was pregnant with me...
私がおなかにいるって
分かったとき…
（ハチマキ）そういや
「コスモノーツ」で読んだな
Come to think of it, I've read
about them in Cosmonauts.
ルナリアンには
生まれつき低重力障害がある
Lunarians are born with damage
from low gravity disorder.
So even though they seem at first glance
to be growing big, their muscles, bones,
だから
見た目は大きくなるけど―
骨や筋肉 心肺機能が
それに 全然ついていけない
...and cardiovascular functions are completely
unable to support a body that size.
All done!
（ノノ）終わった
Bodies that can't withstand
Earth's gravity...
（ハチマキ）
地球の重力には耐えられない体
It's pretty cool that I come
from the moon, huh?
月が故郷なんてすごいでしょ？
自慢なんだ
I'm proud of it.
（ハチマキ）
ノノ 両親を恨んだりしないのか？
Nono, don't you ever hate
your parents for this?
Haven't you ever wished
you could live on Earth?
地球で暮らしたいって思わない？
No matter how nice a place Earth is, there's
no point if you're just gonna live there.
地球がどんなにいい所でも―
ただ暮らしてるだけじゃ
意味ないもん
But I already made up my mind that when
I go to Earth for the first time,
でもね 最初に地球に行くときは
海で泳ぐって決めてんの
...l'm gonna go swimming
in the ocean!
あっ…
Besides, since my body's never experienced
Earth conditions, studying how it develops...
それにね 地球を知らない
私の体の成長記録が―
宇宙生活病の研究に
役立ってるんだ
...is telling the doctors a lot about
space habitation sickness.
その役目が落ち着くまで
月を離れるつもりはないよ
I don't plan on leaving the moon
until that job is done.
Plus, every time they learn something new,
my body gets stronger!
それに 研究が進むたびに
私の体も丈夫になってるしね
それから
地球は暮らしたい所じゃない
Also, I don't want
to live on Earth.
I just want to go see it because
I've never been there.
行ったことがないから
行ってみたいとこ
私が暮らすのは ここ
This is the place
I call home.
♪～
（ハチマキ）ここが…
This is home?
（ハチマキ）あっ…
What do you think, Hachi?
This is my ocean!
どう？ ハチマキ 私の海
いいでしょ？
Pretty neat, huh?
Sorry, but to me,
its just a desert.
（ハチマキ）残念だけど
俺には ただの砂漠だ
あっ…
What're you waiting for?!
Hurry up! C'mon!
どうしたの？ 早くおいでよ ほら
ほら！
C'mon!
（ノノの笑い声）
（ハチマキ）あっ…
You can only see up to magnitude four stars
on Earth, right, Hachimaki?
（ノノ）地球じゃ ４等星までしか
見えないんでしょ？ ハチマキ
あっ あれでしょ？
Look! That's the supernova that they've
been talking about on the news!
こないだ ニュースでやってた
超新星爆発って
リゲルとシリウスを通る
線の先にあるやつだよね
It's that light that's along the line
running through Rigel and Sirius, right?
（ハチマキ）俺にとっては―
To me, the moon is nothing but
an empty desert wasteland.
ただの何もない
砂漠でしかない この月
But to Nono at least,
this place is more than that.
でも少なくとも ノノにとっては
ただの砂漠じゃない
要するに わがままで冷たい
宇宙ってやつと―
I guess it's all a question of how we look
at this selfish, cold universe we live in.
どう向き合っていくかって
ことなんだろうな
Right, Nono?
なあ？ ノノ
Looks like your leg
is as good as new.
（タナベ）
足 すっかりいいみたいですね
（ハチマキ）ああ まあな
Yeah, I guess.
（フィー）休暇も終わりね
Well, vacation's over.
The old daily grind is waiting.
また 仕事漬けの毎日よ
覚悟してもらうから
You better make your
peace with that.
Make my peace?
覚悟なら―
I already did that.
もう できてるよ
Still, it's a vast ocean
out here...
広い海だな しかし
♪～
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
♪グッと水を飲み干し
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
A Place to Cling to
（課長）写真
A picture!
A ticket to something!
（ラビィ）何かのチケット
（ユーリ）お金
Money?
Separation money!
手切れ金！
Yes. Things aren't the same
as they were back then.
（ドルフ）
そうだ あのころとは違う
We'll do it ourselves!
俺たちだけで
やってみせるんだ
The signal's still active, right? We still have its location!
信号は生きてるんだろ？
位置は分かってんだ！
Oh, crap!
やっべえ
（タナベ）先輩
Senpai!
（ドルフ）
ちょうどよかった
Perfect timing. I'd like to
discuss something with you.
君に
話しておきたいことがある
あっ…
She's having an affair?!
不倫ってこと？